‫All right.
‫So we're going to go ahead and get started here.
‫Now, I'm going to keep the final project open just as a reference so that I can point to you guys.
‫Like when I'm creating the HTML in CSS, I can show you exactly what I'm doing in the final project.
‫And like I said in the last video, a lot of times you'll get the design beforehand and you'll just
‫have to use it as a reference and create the HTML and CSS.
‫So we'll kind of take that approach.
‫And I'm also going to for now have the browser and the text editor open at the same time.
‫I don't like how narrow this is, but at the same time, I want you to to see to see them both.
‫If we get to a point where we're creating stuff like this and it doesn't look good when it's this narrow,
‫then I'll make it bigger.
‫So first thing we want to do is create a project folder so you can put that anywhere in your system.
‫I'm going to go to my desktop and I'm just going to call this folder.
‫Let's do hotel underscore website and we can open this in V's code.
‫So let's say open folder and we want hotel website.
‫It's completely empty.
‫And I'm going to create, first of all, a folder for our images and you can call this images or IMG
‫is another common convention, so I'm going to use that.
‫And then we want to get all the image resources that you downloaded in the first video of this section,
‫which I have right here.
‫And we want to put those into our IMG folder.
‫So let's go ahead and select all these and bring them into IMG.
‫Oops.
‫What happened?
‫There we go.
‫All right.
‫So now that those are in there, we can close these up and go back into VS code.
‫And now you can see I have all the images here.
‫So next thing we'll do is create our page structure.
‫As you can see, we have three pages home about in contact.
‫Now, remember, in the beginning of the the HTML basics section, I said that when you have a home
‫page of a website, you need to call it index HTML because when you go to something whatever dot com,
‫it's going to look for that file as the home page.
‫So let's say indexed HTML as a new new file.
‫I click to this icon and we might as well create the rest of the html pages.
‫So we'll do html.
‫About html dot html.
‫Let's do contact dot HTML.
‫And we're also going to need our CSS, our stylesheet and we're not going to be putting our our CSS
‫in the HTML like we did in the sandbox.
‫I only did that for convenience.
‫When you have a project, you want to create separate style sheets and generally you want a separate
‫folder that contains those.
‫So I'm going to click this folder icon and create a folder called CSS.
‫And then inside there I'm going to create a new file called Style CSS.
‫And the name style is it doesn't matter what you call this, but style main CSS.
‫These are common conventions for main style sheets, but it doesn't it doesn't really matter.
‫So now that we have that, that's basically our our website structure.
‫So we're going to head into the index HTML we can close up about and contact for now, but let's open
‫up our style sheet as well.
‫So we have these two files open and let's generate our head body tags.
‫So exclamation enter tab and we'll change the title here to let's say hotel beat.
‫And usually you'll have like some kind of separator, like a dash or a, or a pipe character.
‫And then if you're, if you're focused on search engines like you want to you want to rank for, let's
‫say, Boston Hotel, you might put something like that here as long as it makes sense.
‫But we're just going to put welcome because it's the home page and you'll probably want to put some
‫meta tags in here like description.
‫I'm not going to do this for every project we create, but I'll do it for this one just because it's
‫the first.
‫So let's say name, description and let's do content equals.
‫And then I'll just say Welcome to the most.
‫Extraordinary hotel in
‫Boston, Massachusetts.
‫So that's our description.
‫Let's do another meta tag.
‫This will be our keyword.
‫So we want to do name equals keywords and for the content you'd probably do something like hotel, whatever,
‫the location.
‫So something like Boston Hotel, New England Hotel and whatever it may be, whatever keywords.
‫Describe this page.
‫All right.
‫Now, in addition to that, we want to link our stylesheet.
‫So we use a link tag.
‫And if I use Emit, if I do link enter or link tab, it'll automatically put in the REL attribute.
‫So the REL is going to be equal to stylesheet because we're just telling it that we're importing a stylesheet
‫here, CSS file and then in the a ref, we want to point to that file.
‫Now remember we put it inside of a folder called CSS.
‫So we want to say CSS slash style CSS.
‫Och.
‫And then we can get started with the the body here.
‫Now it's important to mention that everyone has their own style.
‫Everyone has their own naming conventions and how they want to structure tags.
‫For instance, what I'm going to do is have a header tag, so I'll just put it in header.
‫And inside my header I want the navigation and the showcase.
‫I want this whole area to be the header, but it's fine if you would have just this inside the header
‫tag and then maybe have section for this, you're going to see you're going to see different styles
‫when you're looking at different HTML and you're going to develop your own style.
‫What I do here is just what I like to do and I like to think that it's, it's, it's okay.
‫And hopefully guys don't mind the way that I do things, but I just want to, I want, I want to make
‫it clear that every developer has their own style of doing things and not just HTML, any kind of programming,
‫anything like that.
‫So like I said, I want the nav the nav bar in here.
‫So I'm going to create a nav tag and I'm actually going to give this an ID of nav bar.
‫And inside the nav bar, we're going to have the logo, this right here, which is just an H one.
‫And then we're going to have our our navigation, which is our unordered list.
‫So let's put an H one, which I'm actually going to give a class of logo.
‫And that's another thing that is different depending on the developer is is how you use IDs in classes.
‫I could easily call this a class and this an ID.
‫That's fine.
‫The one major rule that I would say you should never break is don't have more than one ID like don't
‫have another idea of nav bar on the same page.
‫But I mean some people you will use just classes.
‫I tend to use IDs for stuff that I won't have duplicates of and that kind of surround everything else
‫that they're parents of other things.
‫For instance, we have the H one and the UL in here, the NAV surrounds them.
‫So I'm going to use an ID here.
‫So for the logo we're just going to do h, b, t, and usually you'll have your logo go to your home
‫page like you'll see if I click on if I hover over it, it's a link and it goes back to the home page.
‫So if I'm on a boat and I click that it take me back.
‫So we want to surround this in an a tag and we want this to go to index dot HTML.
‫All right.
‫Make sure that you're closing a tag is on the other side of the the beat.
‫I'm just going to close this sidebar up to give me some more room as well.
‫So that's our H one.
‫Now we want the UL right here.
‫So let's do UL list item.
‫And then in each list item, we'll have a link.
‫This is going to go to index dot HTML and this is going to be our home page.
‫I'm going to do a control option down or control all down on a Windows machine and let's do a bout and
‫say about HTML contact.
‫Contact.
‫So there's our nav bar.
‫Now let's open this in live server.
‫And it's going to look horrible because we have no CSS.
‫So that's what we're going to do now is we're going to jump to the CSS.
‫And that's another thing that that varies is sometimes you might do all of your HTML on the whole page
‫and then start your CSS or you can do what we're going to do and go by basically component by component.
‫So the nav bar, then we'll move to the showcase, then to this part, that part and so on.
‫So let's jump into Styles, CSS.
‫And in addition to the nav bar styling, I want to do just some of the core basic styling like the body
‫tag and stuff like that.
‫So I am going to add a CSS reset.
‫So I'm going to put an asterisk here, which means we're grabbing everything and we're going to clear
‫out the margin and padding the default margin and padding that the browser puts on every on a lot of
‫different elements.
‫As soon as I save that, you'll see that it changes the UL, the heading, that stuff, the margin goes
‫away.
‫And then I also want to add a box sizing property.
‫Oops.
‫And we're going to set that to border box because when we have boxes that have padding like this right
‫here, I don't want the padding to add to the actual width of the box.
‫So that's pretty important.
‫So next we'll have our main styling.
‫And what I mean by main is just like core elements like the body links, headings, paragraph, all
‫that stuff, anything that really doesn't have a class or an ID.
‫So for the body and a lot of times when you style the body, you'll put in the HTML as well.
‫So HTML body and then I'm just going to set the font family to I'm going to use one of these presets
‫for vs code.
‫We'll use this Segou UI to home a Geneva and then let's set the line height to I'm going to set it kind
‫of high.
‫So 1.7 M And now that I saved, you can see that there's a little more spacing in between the lines.
‫Next thing we'll do is the links.
‫I want all links by default unless unless the class or ID specifies.
‫Otherwise I want them to have a color of three, three, three and I also want to remove the underline.
‫So we'll do text decoration none and we'll save that also the headings.
‫So I'm going to say h one, h two, h three.
‫I want spacing underneath.
‫So if we look at our final project, so like right here, you can see the spacing here, spacing here
‫because we move, we remove the default margin and padding, there's not going to be any spacing.
‫So we need to add that ourselves.
‫So I'm actually going to do padding bottom 20 pixels and then for paragraphs, remember paragraphs by
‫default have a margin, but we just removed it with the reset.
‫So I'm just going to re add ten pixel margin on the top and bottom.
‫Remember, if we do it this way, this is top and bottom, this is left and right.
‫So those are the those are the core styles.
‫Now let's move on to the actual nav bar.
‫So what was it, an ID?
‫Yeah.
‫So we did ID nav bar.
‫Let's put a comment in here just to kind of organize things and we'll say nav bar, I'm going to set
‫the background color or background to three, three, three.
‫I'm going to set the color to white.
‫And let's see, what else are we going to do?
‫Let's do an overflow auto so that the background shows no matter what.
‫And we'll save that and notice that that we can't read the text even though we put color here, because
‫the all the text, it's all links.
‫And if you have links, you have to you have to add the colors specifically to those links.
‫So remember we have a logo, so I'm going to do nav bar class logo.
‫I want to style that link and then any other links in the nav bar.
‫So let's do comma nav bar.
‫Actually, you know what we'll just do just do nav bar a there's no need to do that.
‫And let's say color white and save.
‫And now we can actually see the text.
‫So let's see.
‫Next thing we want to do is align the logo to the left and we want the the UL to be on the right.
‫So let's add some floats for that.
‫And I would recommend using something like Flexbox, but we haven't gotten to that yet, so we're just
‫going to use floats.
‫So let's grab the nav bar h one and let's do float left.
‫I'm also going to add some padding to the top to push it down a little bit.
‫Let's do 20 pixels.
‫We'll save that.
‫Now the UL.
‫We also want to float that.
‫We want to float that to the right.
‫So let's say nav bah ul.
‫We're going to do a couple other things too.
‫We want to remove the bullets.
‫So let's say list style none and we'll set the margin to zero.
‫Pat Actually, we don't have to do that because we added the reset.
‫So let's just do float right and save.
‫And now that's floated over to the right.
‫So the list items right now are going vertical.
‫We want them to go horizontal.
‫So let's grab on to those.
‫We'll say nav bar ul ly or you could just do nab bar ly.
‫It's up to you.
‫I like to just keep it kind of organized like that.
‫So for the list items, we want to float them all to the left and save and then everything else that
‫we style.
‫As far as these links, it's going to be on the a tag inside.
‫So let's do that.
‫Let's say nav bar.
‫You ll see a.
‫And we want to display them as blocks so that we can add padding.
‫And we want to do 20 pixels all around.
‫If I save that, it kind of pushes them right into place.
‫We get 20 pixels all around.
‫Let's make sure there are lines centered.
‫So we'll say text a line center and what else do we want to do?
‫I think that's it.
‫Now, I do want to have a hover state.
‫Right now, if I hover over them, nothing happens.
‫So what we can do is take this and just add our pseudo selector of hover.
‫So colon hover.
‫And I'm going to say background.
‫Let's do four, four, four.
‫And let's also make the color a hexadecimal of F, let's do F, seven C, 08a, which is this light
‫brownish tarnish color.
‫So now if I hover over, it looks like that.
‫Now, another thing I want to do is depending on the page we're on, I want it to have that effect as
‫well.
‫If we look at look at the final project, you can see that the home page has that effect.
‫So what we can do is whatever page we're on in the nav bar here, we can add a special class and we're
‫going to add it to the link to the A tag.
‫So since we're on the home page here, let's say class equals and let's call this current.
‫So we'll go back and then I want it to have this same styling.
‫There's no sense in recreating it.
‫Let's just put a comma so that it affects both and we'll grab this and then just add the class of current.
‫And you usually want to put this on a new line just to keep it clean and save.
‫And now notice the home page has that.
‫Now, before we move on, I just want to show you one thing.
‫If we stretch this out really far, it's always on the very edge here, and I don't want that.
‫Usually what you'll do is you'll have a container and move it into the middle.
‫And we don't want to wrap a container around everything because then the black bar will actually get
‫mad.
‫Added push to the middle.
‫I want the black bar to go all the way across, but I want this stuff to be in the middle.
‫So to do that, what we'll do is add a container class within the nav because remember the nav, the
‫ID nav bar is where that background is.
‫So within that we want to have a container class and we want to move the H one and the UL into that
‫class and save and then we'll style it.
‫So let's add the container.
‫I'm actually going to put the container up top because it's kind of a utility class, meaning you can
‫use it all around.
‫So let's put a comment here and say we'll just say utilities or utility classes.
‫And we'll do container.
‫So remember margin auto.
‫I want to do that.
‫That's going to push it all to the middle.
‫But we need to have some kind of width.
‫So for the width we want to use max width because we want it to be somewhat responsive, as responsive
‫as we can make it without going into stuff we haven't talked about yet, like media queries.
‫And we're going to set that to 1100 pixels.
‫That'll be the max width.
‫All right.
‫And then let's see, let's add in overflow auto just so it always shows the background doesn't go outside
‫of it.
‫And then some padding I want to do padding.
‫Let's do zero, top and bottom.
‫And I just want left and right to have 20 pixels padding.
‫So let's save that and notice that now it's not right up against the edge.
‫And if I bring this, if I bring the browser out.
‫It's right.
‫When it hits 1100 pixels, it stops.
‫That's the max width.
‫And yet the black bar is still goes all the way across.
‫Now, I just want to show you something, and you guys don't have to do this, but if we had the container
‫on the outside of the nav bar, so have that.
‫And then the div the ending can div for the container outside of the nav bar and save.
‫Now the background doesn't reach all the way across because it's restricted inside the container.
‫And I don't like the way that that looks.
‫Websites from like you know like the early 2000s looked like that where everything was in this this
‫container and then you had some like funky background over here.
‫Nowadays, you want your backgrounds to extend all the way across and you want to just put your content
‫inside containers.
‫And that's another reason why it's a class and not an ID is because we're going to be using this container
‫class throughout throughout the site.
‫All right.
‫So let's just bring that back how it was that it's.
‫And there we go.
‫So that's it.
‫That's our nav bar.
‫So in the next video, we're going to start on the showcase area right here.